Simon Liu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute. NIHBC 10 - CRC BG RM 3-2551 10 Center Dr

Bethesda, MD 20892

聞 simon.liu@nih.gov - ☒ nhgri/mgb

github/simonliu99 - orcid/0000-0002-1182-5492

🛅 linkedin/simonliu99 - 🗏 google/scholar

Summary

I am a postbaccalaureate IRTA fellow at the National Institutes of Health interested in deep learning algorithms that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves applying natural language processing to public and private datasets to build models for extracting patient and language annotators. I am a member of the Medical Genomics Unit at the National Human Genome Research Institute.

Education

B.S., Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD.

08/2017 - 05/2021

Also completed B.S. major requirements for Computer Science Honors: Upsilon Pi Epsilon, general honors, Dean's list

GPA: 3.69

Research Experience

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD. 07/2021 - present

With Benjamin Solomon

Software Engineer, Neuroplastic Surgery Research Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, 02/2020 - 05/2021

MD, USA.

With Chad Gordon.

Received Provost's Undergraduate Research Award 2020-21 [award] [news]

Laboratory Assistant, STAR-ORC, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA. 07/2018 - 03/2020

With Junfang Wu

Research Analyst, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 12/2018 - 03/2020

With Susan Hutfless

Volunteer Experience

Care Coordinator, Pan Asian Volunteer Health Clinic, Chinese Culture and Community Service Center, 10/2021 - present Gaithersburg, MD.

With Kate Lu and Yaoyao Zhu

Publications

A list is also available on Google Scholar and Publons.

Journal Articles

Ledgister Hanchard, S. E.*, Dwyer, M. C.*, **Liu, S.***, Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R. L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B. D. (2022). Scoping review and classification of Deep Learning in Medical Genetics.

Genetics in Medicine. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gim.2022.04.025 *Equal contributions. [pdf]

Duong, D., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Hanchard, S. E., **Liu, S.**, Solomon, B. D., & Waikel, R. L. (2022). Neural networks for classification and image generation of aging in genetic syndromes. Frontiers

in Genetics, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.864092 [pdf]

Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., Khan, N., Cao, T., He, J., Lei, Z., Matyas, J. J., Sabirzhanov, B., Liu, S., Li, H., Stoica,

B. A., Loane, D. J., Faden, A. I., & Wu, J. (2020). Delayed microglial depletion after spinal cord injury reduces chronic inflammation and neurodegeneration in the brain and improves neurological recovery in male mice. Theranostics, 10(25), 11376–11403. https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.49199 [pdf]

Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., He, J., Cao, T., Sabirzhanov, B., Li, H., **Liu, S.**, Wu, L. J., & Wu, J. (2021). The voltage-gated proton channel Hv1 plays a detrimental role in contusion spinal cord injury via extracellular

acidosis-mediated neuroinflammation. Brain, behavior, and immunity, 91, 267–283.

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.10.005 [pdf]

Conference Papers

Kenet, A., Mahadevan, E., Elangovan, S., Yan, J., Siddiq, K., **Liu, S.**, Ladwa, A., Narayanan, R., Dakkak, J., Benassi, T., Ng, K., & Manbachi, A. (2020). Flexible piezoelectric sensor for real-time image-guided

C-1

J-3

J-2

J-1

	https://doi.org/10.111//12.25488/3 [pdt]	
Meeting Abstracts	Hutfless, S. M., Chu, D., Liu, S. , & Kalloo, A. N. (2020). Predictors of ERCP-associated infections in outpatient hospitals. Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, 91(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gie.2020.03.3314 [pdf] Hutfless, S. M., Chen, PH., Miller, S. D., Josephson, M., Joseph, S., Urrunaga, N., Kedia, S., Liu, S. , Arya, N., Hobstetter, L., Persad, P., Yeretssian, G., & Brant, S. R. (2020). Would K50* by any other name smell so sweet? A systematic review of claims-based Crohn's disease case definitions. Gastroenterology, 158(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/s0016-5085(20)31712-1 [pdf]	A-2 A-1
Presentations	Liu, S. , Ledgister Hanchard, S., Dwyer, M.C., , Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R.L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B.D. Applications of deep learning in medical genetics. Poster presented at: NIH Virtual Postbac Poster Day 2022; Bethesda, MD. [poster] [pdf]	P-1
Selected Honors	Linda Trinh Memorial Award , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA Project: COVID-19 PPE Manufacturing Proposal: Consortium for 3D-Printed Headbands for Face Shields With Y. Bai, J. Feitelberg, K. Hu, S. Kumar, K. Leo, J. Li, C. Shallal, and N. Zhang	05/2021 [blog] [news]
	Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award Runner Up, Deep Learning course, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Project: Detection and Segmentation of Pneumothoraces in Chest X-ray. [report] [ppt] [award] With F. Shao, Y. Huang, and A. Harmalkar.	12/2020
	Provost's Undergraduate Research Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Project: Implementing Electronic Beam Steering in an Implantable Ultrasound Device [award] [news] With Chad Gordon.	11/2020
	Upsilon Pi Epsilon , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. International Honor Society for the Computing and Information Disciplines	10/2020
	Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, Maryland State Department of Education, Rockville, MD, USA.	06/2017
Selected Press	Stokel-Walker, Chris. "Amid war fears, archivists are racing to preserve Ukraine's internet" Input Mag. February 18, 2022.	2022
	Calabresi, Kaitlyn. "Interview with Health 3D" TCO Labs. November 20, 2019. Sangana, Neha. "Conference highlights student startups in Md." The Johns Hopkins News-Letter. November 15, 2018.	2019 2018
Selected Coursework	Computer Integrated Surgery I Computer Integrated Surgery II Machine Learning Machine Learning: Deep Learning Biomedical Data Science Precision Care Medicine I Precision Care Medicine II Foundations of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics	
Extracurricular Experience	Course Assistant, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Vice President of Finance, Alpha Kappa Psi, Rho Psi Chapter, Baltimore, MD, USA Pledge Educator, Alpha Kappa Psi, Rho Psi Chapter, Baltimore, MD, USA	08/2020 - 05/2021 11/2019 - 12/2020 05/2019 - 11/2019

colonoscopies: a solution to endoscopic looping challenges in clinic. Proc. SPIE 11315, Medical Imaging 2020: Image-Guided Procedures, Robotic Interventions, and Modeling, 1131520 (16 March 2020).

https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2548873 [pdf]

Metadata

This document lives online at https://simonliu.dev/markdown-cv/.

Head of Manufacturing, Health 3D, LLC, Baltimore, MD, USA.

A downloadable version can be found at https://simonliu.dev/files/liu_cv.pdf.

04/2018 - 05/2021

Based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp. MIT License.

Last updated: May 2022